Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.
MSS18630
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
Feinberg, Charles E.
prose poetry Manuscripts
Library of Congress The Library of Congress, Manuscripts Division Room LM101, James Madison Building 101 Independence Ave., S.E. Washington, D.C. 20540-4680 http://www.loc.gov
This catalog was created from the original finding aid created by the Library of Congress and digital images created by the The Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers are held at the Library of Congress.
Restrictions on Original Materials:
Please consult with the Library of Congress.
Alternative Format:
This collection has been microfilmed and comprises 38 microfilm reels. Digital images of some items are available in the "Manuscripts" section of the Walt Whitman Archive. The paper documents comprise 28,000 items.
Scope and Content
The Feinberg-Whitman Collection includes materials relating to Walt Whitman's life and his literary career. Whitman's method of composition can be seen through a wide variety of material in the collection, including handwritten manuscript drafts, edited proofs and offprints, notebooks, diaries, and commonplace books. Materials in the collection illustrate Whitman's development as a writer and provide a strong foundation for scholarship in multiple areas of investigation.
In addition to a strong focus on Whitman's work, the collection also provides documents that relate to his personal life, including correspondence among family, friends, and colleagues. The correspondence includes several hundred letters written by Whitman as well as those he received. The collection also contains photographs and personal artifacts, such as Whitman's walking stick.
Charles Feinberg's correspondence relating to the quarterly Walt Whitman Review, documents pertaining to selected publications about Whitman, and items that detail exhibits based on items from the collection are also included. The collection also includes the papers of Richard Maurice Bucke, Charles E. Feinberg, John H. Johnston, William Douglas O'Connor, and Horace and Anne Montgomerie Traubel.
This catalog includes item-level descriptions of only those documents deemed poetry and/or prose manuscripts.
Biographical Information
Charles Evan Feinberg was born on September 27, 1899 in London, England. He moved with his family to Peterborough, Ontario, Canada in his youth. As one of Samuel and Jane Stocker Feinberg's eight children, Feinberg began working at age twelve to help support his family. His formal education ended after the seventh grade, but he continued to educate himself independently, and he developed a keen interest in American literature, including,most significantly, Walt Whitman. He first read Whitman's poetry in William M. Rossetti's American Poems, and he began constructing his vast Whitman collection at age seventeen with the purchase of a letter for $7.50 (a third of Feinberg's weekly income).
Feinberg emigrated to the United States in 1923 and found a home in Detroit, Michigan. His work in the home heating oil industry provided the resources necessary to develop and expand his Whitman collection. Feinberg purchased letters, postcards, notebooks, and other items created by Whitman, which document the poet's life and literary career. His efforts resulted in the largest and most comprehensive Whitman collection in the world. In addition to Whitman materials, Feinberg also collected Judaica and the works of many other eminent writers, including Robert Frost.
Feinberg's independent work as a book collector and scholar earned him honorary doctorates in humane letters from Southern Illinois University, Carbondale, the University of Detroit, and St. Thomas University in Miami, and the S. Y. Agnon Gold Medal for intellectual achievement from Hebrew University. He wrote articles on Whitman and regularly guest-lectured in college classrooms.
Feinberg, who claimed to be a "custodian, not a possessor" of his vast collection, variously sold and donated the materials in this collection over a number of years. He died in 1988.
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- Diaries, Diary Notes, and Address Books, 1863-91, undated (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3)
  The first series includes diaries, diary notes, address books, notebooks, and commonplace books that are arranged by type of material and then chronologically. Daybooks or memorandum books kept by Whitman are also included in this series.
  - [September & October 1863], loc.00149; xxx.00187; poetry prose handwritten about 21 leaves 10 x 7 cm (Box 1, Folder Address Books 1863, Sept.–Oct.)
    A notebook bound by Whitman and tied with red ribbon. It contains addresses of many soldiers hospitalized at Armory Square Hospital in Washington. Short case histories follow most of the names. Also contains trial lines for the poem Vigil Strange I Kept on the Field One Night, first published in 1865 (see images 7, 11-14 and 16 for material related to Vigil Strange I Kept on the Field One Night).
  - [Hospitals Culpepper], 1863–1864; loc.00485; xxx.00502; xxx.00890; xxx.00891; prose 32 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder Diaries, 1863–1864, hospital notebooks (2 vols.))
    A Civil War diary in which Whitman recorded notes relating to his experiences in Washington D.C. during 1863. Some of these notes were used in A Case from Second Bull Run, a short piece about the death of John Mahay, first published in the 11 December 1864 issue of the New-York Times under the title Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers. Visits Among Army Hospitals, At Washington, on the Field, and here in New-York. Whitman included this paragraph in Memoranda During the War ( 1876 ) and Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882 ). Other portions of this diary contributed directly to Memoranda During the War and others were first published in Letter from Washington. Our National City, after all, has Some Big Points of Its Own—Its Suggestiveness Today—The Figure of Liberty Over the Capital—Scenes, both Fixed and Panoramic—A Thought on Our Future Capital, New-York Times, 4 October 1863.
  - Hospital book 12, 1864; loc.04695; xxx.00472; xxx.00977; prose 40 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder Diaries, 1863–1864, hospital notebooks, (2 vols.))
    A homemade notebook containing hospital and Civil War notes that Whitman recorded between February and May 1864. The entry which begins, "I find this in my notes" (see images 35, 36, and 38) was revised and used in Some War Memoranda. Jotted Down at the Time, which appeared in North American Review ( January 1887 ). This piece was reprinted in November Boughs ( 1888 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The entry which begins, "ah if it might prove" (see image 64) was used in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–1876 ), and later appeared as Down at the Front in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [Two Rivulets], 1876-1886; loc.00150; xxx.00793; poetry more than 17 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder Address Books, 1876-86 (3 v.))
    An address book filled with names and addresses, notes, figures, lists, and trial lines for poems and prose. Contained within the address book are trial lines, which Whitman labeled "Old Proverb," called [I'd make the Songs of the Nation] (see image 26). Also in this notebook is a note entitled Death of Lincoln describing ambitions for a piece on that topic (see image 5).
  - [Glendale birthdays], 1876-1886; loc.04691; xxx.00794; poetry about 22 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder Address Books, 1876-86 (3 v.))
    An address book filled with names and addresses, figures, lists, and notes describing various spring blossoms (see image 44). The relationship of this notebook to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - Diary in Canada, 1880; loc.00151; xxx.00331; poetry handwritten (Box 2, Folder June-Aug. 1880. Diary in Canada Vol. II.)
    Whitman's diary from his trip to Canada in 1880. William White, in his edition of Whitman's Daybooks and Notebooks, noted a relationship between material in this notebook and the poem The Pilot in the Mist.
- General Correspondence, 1841-92, undated (Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
  The general correspondence contains letters sent by Whitman and those he received. Other types of materials in the correspondence include postcards, telegrams, memoranda, and materials enclosed within correspondence. The items are arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically.
  - The Beauty of the Ship, 1876; loc.00499; xxx.00454; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder Buchanan, Robert. Apr. 1876-Jan 1877, & undated.)
    A cancelled, early draft of The Beauty of the Ship written on the verso of an 1876 letter from Whitman to Robert Buchanan.
  - [nor humility's book], 1868; loc.00505; xxx.00727; poetry handwritten 2 leaves (Box 9, Folder Doyle, Peter. Oct. 14, 1868.)
    A draft of a poem on the verso of an 1868 draft letter to Peter Doyle. The poem has been published posthumously under the title [Nor Humility's Book].
  - [Life], 1888; loc.00154; xxx.00728; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 16, Folder Smith, Robert Pearsall. May 7, 1888.)
    A draft of an unpublished poem on the verso of an 1888 letter to Robert Pearsall Smith. The relationship of this draft to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - [One main], about 1887; loc.03853; xxx.00410; xxx.00995; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 16, Folder Smith, Robert Pearsall)
    Clipping, with handwritten revisions, of a passage from A Backward Glance on My Own Road, which had been published in the January 5, 1884 issue of The Critic. This passage was incorporated into My Book and I, which was first published in the January 1887 issue of Lippincott's Monthly Magazine. It was also retained when Whitman used these and two other earlier essays (How 'Leaves of Grass' Was Made and How I Made a Book) to fashion A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and reprinted in the so-called deathbed edition of 1891–1892. It is unclear whether this manuscript was created in the processes that produced My Book and I or if it dates from the later work to create A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads.
- Literary File, 1841-1919, undated (Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37)
  The literary series includes notes, outlines, trial lines, manuscript drafts, proofs and offprints, printed materials, correspondence and other items relating to Whitman's poems, books, speeches, lectures, and articles. The material has been split into distinct subseries based on the literary form. Book materials include handwritten manuscripts drafts, notes, proofs, correspondence, printing and binding statements that are arranged by title. Also included are miscellaneous materials that relate to Whitman's publications, particularly Leaves of Grass. The poetry materials contain trial lines and titles, handwritten manuscript drafts, proofs and offprints, and related printed matter. The prose material includes handwritten manuscript drafts, notes, proofs and offprints, and selected printed materials that relate to Whitman's published and unpublished writings.
  - [Rough MS of Democratic Vistas], about 1871; loc.05655; xxx.00524; prose poetry 65 leaves handwritten (Box 20, Folder Democratic Vistas (1871), Manuscript draft)
    A rough, and heavily revised draft of Democratic Vistas, first published in 1871 and included in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the verso of page 30 is loc.00144, [To What You Said], a poetry draft described separately in this finding aid.
  - Complete Poems & Prose of Walt Whitman, about 1888; loc.00044; xxx.00503; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 19, Folder Complete Poems and Prose (1888), Manuscript drafts, Title page)
    A mock title page for Complete Poems & Prose of Walt Whitman, 1855–1888 Authenticated & Personal Book (handled by W.W.) Portraits from Life...Autograph ( 1888 ).
  - [ab't like this], about 1888; loc.00045; xxx.00503; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 19, Folder Complete Poems and Prose (1888), Manuscript drafts, Title page)
  - [let the big], about 1888; loc.00046; xxx.00503; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 19, Folder Complete Poems and Prose (1888), Manuscript drafts, Title page)
  - [To printer], about 1888; loc.00048; xxx.00503; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 19, Folder Complete Poems and Prose (1888), Manuscript drafts, Title page)
  - [To What You Said], about 1860; loc.00144; xxx.00524; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 20, Folder Democratic Vistas. Manuscript Draft. Original Draft.)
    Cancelled draft written in pencil on the verso of page 30 (Whitman's numbering) of a sixty-five page rough draft of Democratic Vistas (see [Rough MS of Democratic Vistas]). [To What You Said] bears a strong relationship to the Calamus poems that were composed between 1857-1860.
  - Good-Bye My Fancy, about 1891; loc.05454; xxx.00459; poetry handwritten typed printed 78 leaves (Box OV 2, Folder Good-Bye My Fancy (1891), Manuscript draft)
    This manuscripts contains 78 pages of text numbered by Whitman, and is housed along with other materials related to Good-Bye My Fancy. To assemble the manuscript for the printer Whitman used proof sheets, newspaper clippings, etc., between manuscript pages, which were written mostly on paper fragments. A Death Bouquet was written on a typewriter and inserted as part of the manuscript. Throughout, innumerable changes, corrections, and directions for the printer appear. The poems included are: Sail Out for Good, Eidólon Yacht!, Lingering Last Drops, Good-bye My Fancy, On, on the Same, Ye Jocund Twain!, My 71st Year, Apparitions, The Pallid Wreath, An Ended Day, Old Age's Ship & Crafty Death's, To the Pending Year (earlier title To the Year 1889 crossed out), Shakspere-Bacon's Cipher, Long, Long Hence (earlier title Under These Poemets crossed out), Bravo, Paris Exposition! (earlier title Bravo, Paris Exhibition! crossed out), Interpolation Sounds, To the Sun-Set Breeze, Old Chants, A Christmas Greeting, Sounds of the Winter, A Twilight Song, When the Full-grown Poet Came, Osceola, A Voice from Death, A Persian Lesson, The Commonplace, 'The Rounded Catalogue Divine Complete,' Mirages, L. of G.'s Purport (which includes three poems originally composed separately, My task, Death dogs my steps, and For us two, reader dear), The Unexpress'd, Grand is the Seen, Unseen Buds, Good-bye My Fancy!, For Queen Victoria's Birthday, Death's Valley, After an Interval, As in a Swoon, L. of G., and After the Argument. Also included are several prose pieces. Also in this folder are a wrapper addressed to "Ferguson Bros. & Co; Printers, Phila.," two statements by Ferguson Bros. to Whitman, a statement dated May 18, 1891, by Grosscup and West, Phila. for the plates of Whitman's portrait to be included in the book (they had been ordered by Traubel), two trial title pages, and a proof portrait from the engraver.
  - Good-Bye My Fancy, about 1891; loc.05452; xxx.00459; poetry prose handwritten printed about 10 leaves (Box OV 2, Folder Good-Bye My Fancy (1891), Manuscript draft)
    Manuscript and corrected print material that was included in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
  - Good-Bye My Fancy, 1891; loc.05458; xxx.00459; poetry printed handwritten 14 leaves (OV 2, Good-Bye My Fancy (1891), Manuscript draft)
    Manuscript and corrected print material that was included in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ). Some leaves are composed of various scraps of paper, including envelopes and pieces of correspondence that have been pasted together to make larger leaves (see images 15 through 20).
  - [appendage leaves—the original (1855 Brooklyn) edition], loc.00749; xxx.00892; xxx.00893; prose 2 leaves handwritten printed (Box 20, Folder Leaves of Grass. 1855 edition. Book reviews. Printed copies with corrections and notations.)
    Printed copies of reviews that were reprinted in Leaves of Grass and that include Whitman's corrections and notations. Walt Whitman a Brooklyn Boy. Leaves of Grass (A Volume of Poems Just Published) was first printed in the 29 September 1855 issue of the Brooklyn Daily Times. Walt Whitman and His Poems was first published in the September 1855 issue of United State Review.
  - [The wild gander leads], about 1855; loc.00507; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 20, Folder L of G (1855). Manuscript Page.)
    A one-page handwritten draft of a portion of Song of Myself, which was published first in 1855. These lines eventually became section 14 and the beginning of section 15 in the final version of Leaves of Grass. On the verso is a long list of words.
  - Leaves of Grass, 1871; loc.04749; xxx.00001; 22 leaves poetry handwritten printed (Box 21, Folder L of G (1871). Page Proofs.)
    Plate proof of the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass with some corrections in Whitman's hand. Images of the versos are unavailable.
  - Leaves of Grass, 1871; loc.07054; xxx.00001; 3 leaves poetry handwritten printed (Box 21, Folder L of G (1871). Plate Proofs.)
    Plate proof of the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass with a few corrections in Whitman's hand. Images of the first two versos are unavilable.
  - Sands at Seventy, about 1888; loc.00174; xxx.00375; poetry handwritten printed 20 leaves 28.5 x 19.7 cm (Box 22, Folder L of G (1888). Page Proofs—Sands at Seventy)
    Proof of Sands at Seventy with some notes in Whitman's hand and in another, unidentified hand. The notes mostly regard pagination and the insertion of the poem Old Age's Lambent Peaks.
  - This first page will be, about 1888; loc.00030; xxx.00460; poetry prose printed handwritten about 62 leaves (Box OV 4, Folder November Boughs, Galley Proofs)
    Sixty-two pages of galley proofs of November Boughs ( 1888 ), with numerous corrections.
  - November Boughs, about 1888; loc.00031; xxx.00460; poetry prose handwritten printed about 14 leaves (Box OV 4, Folder November Boughs, Galley Proofs)
    Galley proofs of November Boughs ( 1888 ), with numerous corrections. Also included is a title page, with printing instructions in Whitman's hand.
  - November Boughs, about 1888; loc.00032; xxx.00460; poetry prose handwritten printed about 21 leaves (Box OV 4, Folder November Boughs, Galley Proofs)
    Galley proofs of November Boughs ( 1888 ), with numerous corrections. Also included is an uncorrected title page, which seems to incorporate the changes Whitman requested on the title page in another set of corrected proofs for November Boughs; compare the title page for this set of proofs with the first image of loc.00031.
  - November Boughs, about 1888; loc.00033; xxx.00460; prose handwritten printed 2 leaves (Box OV 4, Folder November Boughs, Galley Proofs)
    Galley proofs of November Boughs ( 1888 ), with Whitman's corrections.
  - Passage to India, about 1871; xxx.00496; poetry printed handwritten (Box 23, Folder Passage to India. Page Proofs.)
    Page proofs of Walt Whitman's book of 1871, Passage to India, with several (mostly minor) corrections in Whitman's hand.
  - Come, Muse, migrate from Greece and Ionia, about 1871; loc.00380; xxx.00117; poetry handwritten 4 leaves (Box 25, Folder After All, Not to Create Only (1871). Manuscript Drafts and Notes.)
    Four pages of lines later revised and included in After All, Not to Create Only, first published 1871. That poem was later revised and the title changed to Song of the Exposition.
  - [The trilogy], about 1871; loc.00381; xxx.00117; poetry handwritten about 50 leaves (Box 25, Folder After All, Not to Create Only (1871). Manuscript Drafts and Notes.)
    Several notes and drafts with an unknown relationship to one another, but all, at least thematically, resembling the poem first published as After All, Not to Create Only in 1871 (later published as Song of the Exposition). The pages include trial lines for the poem, as well as notes which indicate the general ambitions and themes of the work. Within these pages, other trial titles of the poem are also included: After all, not to command only, After all, not to create but to obey, and After all, not to create or destroy only. On the verso of one of the leaves is a letter from William Black seeking Whitman's autograph.
  - After all, not to create only, about 1871; loc.00382; xxx.00117; poetry handwritten 30 leaves largest 25 x 20 cm (Box 25, Folder After All, Not to Create Only (1871). Manuscript Drafts and Notes.)
    Bound manuscript of After all, not to create only. Although the manuscript contains many revisions, it appears to be relatively near the final draft. Whitman wrote this poem following a request by the Committee on Invitations of the American Institute to deliver an original poem at the opening of the Fortieth Annual Exhibition. After All, Not to Create Only was first published in 1871. It was later revised and the title changed to Song of the Exposition.
  - Come, Muse, migrate from Greece and Ionia, about 1871; loc.00383; xxx.00117; poetry handwritten 10 leaves largest 25 x 20 cm (Box 25, Folder After All, Not to Create Only (1871). Manuscript Drafts and Notes.)
    A relatively clean draft titled Come, Muse, migrate from Greece and Ionia. This material was later incorporated into After All, Not to Create Only, first published in 1871. That poem was later revised and title changed to Song of the Exposition.
  - After All, Not to Create Only, about 1871; loc.05680; xxx.00117; poetry handwritten both 11 leaves (Box 25, Folder After All, Not to Create Only (1871). Proof Sheets)
    Proof sheets printed by Pearson, Washington. Whitman made only one correction (see surface 11). After All, Not to Create Only was first published in 1871. It was later revised and the title was changed to Song of the Exposition.
  - After the Argument, about 1891; loc.00001; xxx.00565; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 9.5 x 21.5 cm (Box 26, Folder After the Argument (1891). A.MS.S. draft)
    A draft of After the Argument. The poem was published first in Lippincott's Magazine, March, 1891.
  - After the Dazzle of Day, about 1888; loc.00002; xxx.00326; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 14 x 14.5 cm (Box 26, Folder After the Dazzle of Day (1888). A.MS. draft)
    This four-line poem was first published in the New York Herald, February 3, 1888. In the lower right-hand corner is the notation: "For Francis Howard Williams, May 1896, Traubel."
  - After the Supper and Talk, 1887; loc.00004; xxx.00376; xxx.00117; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf 28 x 25.5 cm (Box 26, Folder After the Supper and Talk (1888). A.MS. drafts)
    Signed draft of the poem, which was first published in 1887. On the verso is a proof sheet from After All, Not to Create Only with one correction.
  - So Loth to Depart!, about 1887; loc.00003; xxx.00376; xxx.00115; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf 26 x 20 cm (Box 26, Folder After the Supper and Talk (1888). A.MS. drafts)
    Draft of poem later revised and published as After the Supper and Talk in 1887. On verso detached from Leaves of Grass, part of Poem of Joys, first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass, and later published as A Song of Joys. The title Poem of Joys is in Whitman's hand.
  - After the Supper and Talk, about 1887; loc.00175; xxx.00376; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf 12 x 15 cm (Box 26, Folder After the Supper and talk (1887). Proof Sheets.)